The following content is provided under a
Creative Commons license. Your support will
help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high quality educational resources for
free. To make a donation or to view
additional materials from hundreds of MIT
courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare at ocw
.mit .edu. So this is a pretty key lecture.
This lecture is about principal component
analysis, PCA, which is a major tool in
understanding a matrix of data. So
what is PCA about? Well, first of all,
let me remember what was the whole point
of yesterday's lecture, the singular value
decomposition that any matrix A could be
broken into R rank one pieces, R being the
rank of the matrix. And each piece has a u
times a v transpose. And the good special
thing is the u's are orthonormal, and also
the v's are orthonormal. OK, so that's the
whole matrix. But we have a big matrix, and
we want to get the important information
out of it, not all the information. People
say if in machine learning, if you've
learned all the training data, you haven't
learned anything, really. You've just
copied it all in. The whole point of neural
nets and the process of machine learning
is to learn important facts about the
data. And now here, we're at the most basic
stage of that. And I claim that the
important facts about the matrix are the
largest k singular values, the largest k
pieces. We can take k equal 1 would tell us
the largest single piece. But maybe we have
space and computing power to handle 100
pieces. So I would take k equal 100.
The matrix might have rank thousands. So I
claim that Ak is the best. Now,
here's the one theorem for today.
Ak using the first k pieces of the SVD is
the best approximation to A of rank k. So
I'll write that down. So that really
says why the SVD is perfect. OK, so that
statement says that
if B, another
matrix, has rank k,
then
the distance from A to B, the error you're
making in just using B, that error is
greater than or equal to the
error you make for the best guy.
So that's a pretty straightforward,
beautiful fact. And it goes back to people
who discovered the SVD in the first place.
But then a couple of psychologists gave a
proof in a later paper. And it's often
called the Eckart -Young theorem. There is
the theorem. Isn't that straightforward?
And the hypothesis is straightforward.
That's pretty nice. But of course, we have
to think, why is it true? Why is it true?
And to give meaning to the theorem, we have
to say what these double bars are. Do you
know the right name for this? So that
double bar around a matrix is called the
norm of the matrix, the norm. So I have to
say something about matrix norms. How big
is it? That's a measure of how big it is.
And what I have to say is there are many
different measures of a matrix, how large
that matrix is. Let me tell you, for today,
three possible
measures of a matrix.
So different ways to measure a ma - I'll
call the matrix just A, maybe. But then I'm
going to apply the measure to A minus
B and to A minus AK and show that that is
smaller. So I want to tell you about the
norm of A, about some possible norms of A.
And actually, the norms I'm going to take
today will have the special feature that
they can be computed by the singular
values. So let me mention the L2 norm. That
is the largest singular value. So that's an
important measure of the size of a matrix.
I'm talking here about a general m by n
matrix A. Sigma 1 is an important norm,
often called the L2 norm. And that's where
that index 2 goes. Oh, I should really
start with vectors, norms of vectors, and
then build to norms of matrices. Let me do
norms of vectors over on this side. The L2
norm of a vector, do we know what that is?
That's the regular length of the vector
that we all expect, the square root of v1
squared up to vn squared. The hypotenuse,
the length of the hypotenuse in n
-dimensional space, that's the norm because
of that 2. The L1 norm of a vector is just
add up those pieces. Without squaring and
square rooting them, just add them. That's
the L1 norm. And you might say, why do
we want two norms? Or there are more norms.
Let me just tell you one more. The infinity
norm, and there's a reason for the 1 and
the 2 and the infinity,
is the largest of the v's.
OK. Have you met norms before? I don't
know. These are vector norms that maybe you
have met. Then we're going to have
matrix norms that maybe will be new.
So this is the norm that we usually think
of. But this one has become really, really
important and let me tell you just why. And
then we'll, later section of the notes and
a later lecture in this course, we'll
develop that. This is the L1 norm. So this
is L2, L1, and L infinity. That was off
from the QC. So what's special about this
one? Well, it just turned out, and it was
only discovered in our lifetimes, that when
you minimize some function using the
L1 norm, you minimize some, say, signal to
noise or whatever you minimize,
some function. If you use L1, the winning
vector, the minimizing vector, turns out
to be sparse. And what does sparse mean?
Sparse means mostly zero components.
Somehow, when I minimize in L2, which
historically goes back to Gauss, the
greatest mathematician of all time, when
you minimize something in L2, you do least
squares. And you find that the guy that
gives you the minimum has a lot of
little numbers. A lot of little components,
because when you square those
little ones, they don't hurt much.
But Gauss, so Gauss didn't do least L1
norm. That has different names, basis,
pursuit. And it comes into
signal processing and sensing.
And then it was discovered that if you
minimize, as we'll see, in that norm, you
amazingly get the winning vector is mostly
zeros. And the advantage of that is that
you can understand what its components are.
The one with many small components, you
have no interpretation for that answer.
But for an answer that just has a few non
-zero components, you really see what is
happening. And then this is an important
one, too.
Now I'm going to turn just to, so what's
the property of a norm? Well, you can see
that the norm of C times a vector is,
just multiplying by 6 or 11 or minus pi or
whatever, is the size of C.
Norms have that nice property. They're
homogeneous or whatever word. If you double
the vector, you should double the norm.
Double the length, that makes sense. And
then the important property is
the famous triangle inequality that
if V and W are two sides of a triangle, and
you take the norm of V and add to the norm
of W, the two sides, you get more than the
straight norm along the hypotenuse. Yeah,
so those are properties that we require.
And the fact that the norm is positive,
which is, I won't write down, but it's
important, too. OK, so those are norms. And
those will apply also to matrix norms.
So if I double the matrix, I want to double
its norm. And of course,
that works for the two norm.
So the triangle inequality for this norm is
saying that the largest singular value of
A plus B, two matrices, is less or equal
to the largest singular value of A plus the
largest singular value of B. And we
won't take class time to check minor,
straightforward things like that. So now
I'm going to continue with, there's three
norms that I want
to tell you about.
That's a very important one. Then there is
another norm that's named as an F. And it's
named after Frobenius.
Sorry about that.
And what is that norm? That norm looks at
all the entries in the matrix, just like it
was a long vector. And squares them all and
adds them up. So in a way, it's like the
two norm for a vector. So the squared,
or shall I put square root? Maybe I should.
It's the square root of all the little
people in the matrix. So A1n squared plus
the next A21 squared and so on. You finally
get to Amn squared. You just treat the
matrix like a long vector. And take
the square root just like. So that's the
Frobenius norm. And then
finally, not so well known,
is something that's more like
L1. It's called the nuclear norm.
And not all the faculty would know about
this nuclear norm. So it is the sum of the
sigma of the singular values.
I guess there are them. So
that's where we would stop.
Oh, OK. So those are three norms. Now, why
do I pick on those three norms? And here's
the point. For those three norms, this
statement is true. I could cook up other
matrix norms for which this wouldn't work.
But for these three highly important norms,
this Eckert -Young statement that the
closest rank k approximation is found from
the first k pieces. You see, that's a good
thing. Because this is what we compute from
the SVD. So now we've solved an
approximation problem. We found the best b
is ak. And the point is, it could use any
of those norms. So there would be a, well,
somebody finally came up with a proof that
does all three norms at once. In the notes,
I do that one separately
from Frobenius.
And actually, I found in an MIT thesis, I
was just reading a course six PhD thesis.
And the author, who's speaking
tomorrow or Friday in IDSS,
Dr. Srebro. I found a nice new proof of
Frobenius. And it's in the notes, as well
as an older proof. OK. You know, as I
talk here, I'm not too sure whether it is
essential for me to go through the proof
either in the L2 norm, which takes half a
page in the notes, or in the Frobenius
norm, which takes more. I'd rather you see
the point. The point is that in these
norms, and now, what is special about these
norms of a matrix? These depend only
on the sigmas. Only on the sigmas. Oh, I'll
finish that sentence, because it was true.
These norms depend only on the singular
values. Right? That one, at least, depends
only on the singular value. It's the
largest one. This one is the sum of
them all. This one comes into the Netflix
competition, by the way. This was the right
norm to win zillion dollars in the Netflix
competition. So what did Netflix put?
It did a math competition. It had movie
preferences from many, many Netflix
subscribers. They gave their ranking to a
bunch of movies. But of course, they hadn't
seen, no, none of them had seen all the
movies. So the matrix of rankings,
where you had the ranker and the matrix,
is a very big matrix. But it's got missing
entries. If the ranker didn't see the
movie, he or she isn't ranking it. So
what's the idea about Netflix? They offered
a million dollar prize. And a lot of math
and computer science people fought for that
prize. And over the years, they got higher,
92%, 93%, 94 % right. But it turned out
that this was, well, in the end, you had
to use a little psychology of how people
voted. So it was partly about human
psychology. But it was also a very large
matrix. Problem with an incomplete matrix.
An incomplete matrix. And so it had to be
completed. You had to figure out what would
the ranker have said about the post if he
hadn't seen it, but had ranked several
other movies, like All the President's Men
or whatever, given a ranking to those.
And that's a recommender system, of course.
Prijat pomolri,
flakes competition. But this turned out to
be the right norm to do a minimum problem,
a best, not least squares. These squares
would look at some other norm, but a best
nuclear norm completion of the matrix. And
so now it's being put to much more serious
uses for MRI,
magnetic resonance stuff, when you go in
and get, it's a noisy system, but it gives
an excellent picture of what's going on.
So I'll just write Netflix here. So it gets
in there. And then MRIs.
So what's the point about MRIs?
So if you stay in long enough, you get all
the numbers. There isn't missing data. But
if you, as with a child, you might want to
just have the child in for a few minutes,
then that's not enough to get a complete
picture. And you have, again, missing data
in your matrix of,
in the image from the MRI. So then, of
course, you've got to complete that matrix.
You have to fill in what would the MRI have
seen in those positions where it didn't
look long enough.
And so that's the, the nuclear norm is the
good one for that. OK. So there's, there
will be a whole section on norms. Maybe
just about in Stellar by now. OK. So I'm
not going to, let me just say like,
what does this, what does this say?
I'll just give an example.
Maybe I'll take, start, start with the
example that's in the notes. Suppose K is
2. So I'm looking of, among all rank 2
matrices. And suppose my matrix is 4, 3, 2,
1, and all the rest 0's.
Diagon.
Completed. What would A2 do?
Yeah. It would be 4 and 3. It would pick
the two largest. So I'm looking at AK. This
is K equal to 2. So it has to have rank 2.
This has got rank 4. The biggest pieces are
those.
OK.
So this thing says that if I had any other
matrix B, it would be further away from A2.
May than this guy. Says that this is the
closest. And I just, like, could, could you
think of a matrix that could possibly be
closer and be rank 2? That, rank 2 is the
tricky thing. The, the matrices of rank 2
form a kind of crazy set. If I add a rank 2
matrix to a rank 2 matrix, probably the
rank is up to 4. So, so the rank 2 matrices
are all kind of floating around in little,
in their own little corners. This looks
like the best one. But in the notes, I
suggest, well, you could get a rank 2, a
rank, I could, what about B? What about
this B? For this guy, I could get closer,
maybe not exact, but closer,
maybe by taking 3 .5, 3 .5.
Maybe 1 .5 down here.
OK. So that's a rank 2 matrix. Two little
rank 1s. And on the diagonal, it's better.
3 .5s, I'm only missing by a half. 1 .5s,
I'm missing by a half. So I'm only missing
by a half on the diagonal, where this
guy was missing by 2. So maybe I've found
something better.
But I had to pay a price of these things
off the diagonal to keep the rank low. And
they kill me. So that B will be further
away from A. The error, if I computed A
minus B and computed its norm, I would see
bigger than, bigger than A minus A2. Yeah.
Yeah. So you see the point of the theorem?
That's, that's really what I'm trying to
say. That it's not obvious. You may, you
may feel, well, it's totally obvious. Pick
4 and 3. What else could do it? But it
depends on the norm and so on. So it's not,
not, Eckart Young had to think of a proof
and other people too. OK. So that's, now,
but you could say, also say, object,
that I started with a diagonal matrix here.
That's so special. But what I want to say
is the diagonal matrix is not that special.
Because I could take A, so let me now just
call this diagonal matrix D. Or let me call
it sigma to give it another
sort of appropriate name.
So if I thought of matrices, what I want
to say is, this could be the sigma matrix.
And there could be a U on the left of
it and a sigma on the right of it. So, so
about A is U sigma V transpose. So this is
my sigma. And this is like any orthogonal
matrix U. And this is
like any V transpose.
Right? I'm just saying, here's a whole lot
more matrices. There's just one matrix. But
now I have all these matrices with U's
multiplying on the left and V transpose on
the right. And I ask you this question.
What are the singular values of that
matrix, A? Here, the singular values
were clear, 4, 3, 2, and 1. What are the
singular values of this matrix A when I've
multiplied by an orthogonal guy on both
sides? That's a key question. What are the
singular values of that one? 4, 3, 2, 1.
Didn't change. Why is that?
Because the singular values are the,
because this has a SVD form, orthogonal
times diagonal times orthogonal. And
that diagonal contains the singular values.
Because that might, and our trivial little
example here, actually was all 4 by 4's
that have these singular values. I could,
my whole problem is orthogonally invariant,
a math guy would say. When I multiply
by U or a V transpose or both, the problem
doesn't change. Norms don't change. Yeah,
that's a point. Yeah, I realize it now.
This is the point. If I multiply the matrix
A by an orthogonal matrix U, it has all
the same norms. Doesn't change the
norm. Actually, that was true way back for
vectors.
With this length, with this length, what's
the deal about vectors? Suppose I have a
vector V and I've computed its hypotenuse
and the norm. I've got a vector V times V
in that same 2 norm.
What's special about that? So I took
any vector V and I know what its length is,
hypotenuse. Now I multiply by Q. What
happens to the length? Doesn't change.
Doesn't change.
Orthogonal matrix, you could think of it
as just like rotating the triangle. If you
rotate the triangle in space, the
hypotenuse doesn't change. And we've
checked that because we could, you know,
the check is to square it and then you're
doing QV transpose QV. And you simplify
it the usual way. And then you have Q
transpose Q equal the identity and you're
golden. Yeah, so the result is you get the
same answer as V.
This is my A. If I multiply by a Q, then I
have QU sigma V transpose. And what is
really the underlying point? That QU is an
orthogonal matrix just as good as U. So let
me put this down. QA would be QU sigma
V transpose. And now I'm asking you, what's
the singular value
decomposition for QA?
And I hope I'm actually seeing it. What's
the singular value decomposition of QA?
What are the singular values? What's the
diagonal matrix? Just look there for it.
The diagonal matrix is sigma. What goes on
the right of it? The V transpose. And what
goes on the left of it is QU. Because
that's orthogonal times orthogonal.
So I know that if I multiply two orthogonal
matrices, the result is again orthogonal.
So I can multiply by Q and it only affects
the U part, not the sigma part. And so it
doesn't change any of those norms. OK.
So that's fine. That's what I wanted to say
about the Eckart -Young theorem. Not
proving it, but hopefully giving you an
example
there of what it means that this is the
best rank to approximate that one. OK.
So that's the key math behind PCA. So now
I have to want to, not just have to, but
want to, tell you about PCA. So what's that
about? So we have a bunch of data. And we
want to see. So let me take a
bunch of data. Bunch of data points.
Say points in the plane. So I have a bunch
of data points in the plane. So here's my
data vector. First vector x1.
Well, x, is that a good, maybe v1?
These are just two component guys. v2.
They're just columns with two components.
So I'm just measuring height and age.
And I want to find the relationship between
height and age. So the first row is the
heights of my data. And the second row is
the ages. So I've got,
say, a lot of people.
And these are the heights.
And these are the ages.
And I've got n points in 2 -D.
And I want to make sense out of that. I
want to look for the relationship between
height and age.
I'm actually going to look for a linear
relation between height and age. OK.
So first of all, these are all over
the place. So the first step that a
statistician does is to get mean 0. Get the
average to be 0. So all these points are
all over the place. From row 1, the
heights, I subtract the average height. So
this is A, the matrix I'm really going to
work on, is my matrix A minus the average
height. Well, in all
components. So this
is A, A, A, A. I'm subtracting
the mean. So average height.
And average age. Oh, that was a brilliant
notation. A sub A. Can't beat A sub A.
You see what the matrix has done. This
matrix of two means has just made each row
of A now adds to
row, now adds to what?
If I have a bunch of things, and I've
subtracted off their mean, so the mean or
the average is now 0, then those things
add up to 0. Right. I've just brought these
points into something like here.
This is age. And this is height.
And let's see. And by subtracting, it no
longer is unreasonable to have negative age
and negative height.
So right.
The little kids, when I subtracted off the
average age, they ended up with a negative
age. The older ones ended up still
positive. And somehow, I've got a whole lot
of points. But hopefully, their mean is now
0. Do you see that? I've centered the data
at 0, 0. And I'm looking for what? What
am I looking for here? I'm looking for the
best line.
That's what I want to find.
PCA is a linear business. And
I'm looking for the best line.
And you will say, wait a minute. I know
how to find the best line. Just use the
squares. Gauss did
it. Can't be all bad.
But PCA, and I was giving a talk in New
York when I was just learning about this.
And somebody said, what you're doing with
PCA has to be the same as least squares.
It's finding the best line. And I knew it
wasn't. But I didn't know how to answer the
question best. And now, at least I know
better. So the best line in least squares,
can I remind you about least squares?
Because this is not least squares. The best
line of least squares, so I have some data
points. And I have a best line that goes
through them. And least squares, I don't
always center the data to mean 0. But I
could. But what do you minimize
in least squares? So least squares.
If you remember the picture in linear
algebra books of least squares, you measure
the errors, like
the three errors.
How much you're wrong
at those three points.
Those are the three errors. The difference
between Ax and B. The B minus Ax that you
square. And you add
up those three errors.
And what's different over here? I mean,
there's more points. But that's not the
point. That's not the difference. The
difference is, in PCA, you're measuring
perpendicular to the line. You're adding
up all these little guys, squaring them. So
you're adding up their squares and
minimizing. So the points, you see it's a
different problem. And
therefore, it has a different answer.
And this answer
turns out to involve
the SVD, the sigmas.
Where this answer, you remember
from ordinary linear algebra, just when you
minimize that, you got to an equation that
leads to what equation for the best x? So
do you remember? Yeah, what is it? No?
Everybody should know. And we will actually
see it in this course, because we're
doing the heart of linear algebra here. We
haven't done it yet, though. And tell
me again, what equation do I solve for that
problem? A transpose A.
x hat equal A transpose B.
Called the normal equations.
It's a regression
in statistics language. That's a regression
problem. This is a different problem. Just
so now you see the answer. So
that involves, well, they both involve A
transpose A. That's sort of interesting.
Because you have a rectangular matrix A.
And then sooner or later, A transpose A is
coming. But this involves solving a linear
system of equations. So it's fast. And we
will do it. And it's very important. It's
probably the most
important application in 1806.
But it's not the same as this one. So this
is now in 1806, maybe the last day of the
90s, is PCA. So I didn't put those
letters. Principal Component Analysis, PCA.
Which statisticians have been doing for a
long time. We're not doing something brand
new here. But the result is that we, so
how does the statistic think about this
problem? Or that data matrix?
If you have a matrix of data, two by two
rows and many columns, so many, many
samples,
what, and we've made the mean 0. So that's
the first step a statistician takes, to
check on the mean. What's the next step?
What else does a statistician do with data
to measure how it's sized? There's another
number. There's a number that goes with the
mean. And it's the variance. The mean and
the variance. So somehow, we're going to do
variances. And it will really be involved.
Because we have two sets of data, heights
and ages, we're really
going to have the covariance.
And we're going to have the variance, the
variance matrix. And it will be two by two.
Because it will tell us not only the
variance in the heights. That's the first
thing a statistician would think about.
Some small people, some big people. And
variation in ages, but also the link
between them. How are the height -age
pairs?
Height, does more age go with more height?
And of course, it does. That's the whole
point here. So it's this covariance matrix.
And that covariance matrix, or the sample
covariance matrix,
to give it its full name.
So just touching on statistics for a moment
here. When we see that word sample in the
name, what is that telling us?
Telling us that this matrix is computed
from the samples, not from a theoretical
probability distribution. We might have
a proposed distribution that the height
follows the age by some formula. And
that would give us theoretical variances.
We're doing sample variances, also called
empirical. Covariance matrix. Empirical
says, empirical, that word means from the
information, from the data. So that's what
we do. And it is exactly,
it's A A transpose.
You have to normalize it by the number
of data points. And then for some reason,
that's known to statisticians,
it's n minus 1.
And of course, they've got to be right.
They've been around a long time. And it
should be n minus 1. Because somehow, one
degree of freedom was accounted for when we
took away, when we made the mean 0.
So anyway, no problem. But the n minus 1 is
not going to fit. It's going to affect our
computation here. This is the matrix that
tells us, that's what
we've got to work with.
That's what we've got to work with,
the matrix A A transpose. And then,
so we have this problem. So we have a,
yeah, I guess we really have a minimum
problem. We want to find, yeah, what
problem are we solving? And it's, yeah. So
our problem was not least squares. Not the
same as least squares. Similar, but not the
same. We want to minimize. So
we're looking for that best line.
A g equals some number c times the height.
Times the, yeah. Or height. Maybe it would
have been better to put age here and
height here. We've got two unknowns. So I'm
looking for c. I'm looking for the number
c. Looking for the number c. And with just
two minutes in class left, what is that
number c going to be when I finally get the
problem stated properly and then solve it?
I'm going to learn that the best ratio of
age to height is sigma 1. Sigma 1. That's
the one that tells us how those two are
connected. And the orthogonal,
and what will be the best,
yeah. No, maybe I didn't answer that right.
Maybe I didn't get that right. Because I'm
looking for, I'm looking for the vector
that points in the right way. Yeah. I'm
sorry.
I think the answer is, it's got to be there
in the SVD. I think it's the vector u1.
It's the principal component, u1. Let's
do that properly on Friday. I hope you see,
because this was like the first step away
from the highlights of linear algebra and
problems solved by linear algebra and
practical problems. And my point is that
the SVD solves these. OK.